<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
  <info>
    <name>Oath of the Watchers</name>
    <description>The Paladin Oath of the Watchers from Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</description>
    <author url="http://dnd.wizards.com/products/tabletop-games/rpg-products/tashas-cauldron-everything">Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</author>
    <update version="0.1.4">
      <file name="paladin-watchers.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tregolani/wotc-dnd-content/main/supplements/tashas-cauldron-of-everything/archetypes/paladin-watchers.xml" />
    </update>
  </info>

	<element name="Oath of the Watchers" type="Archetype" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_OATH_OF_THE_WATCHERS">
		<supports>Sacred Oath</supports>
		<description>
			<p>The Oath of the Watchers binds paladins to protect mortal realms from the predators of extraplanar creatures, many of which can lay waste to mortal soldiers. Thus, the Watchers hone their minds, spirits, and bodies to be the ultimate weapons against such threats.</p>
			<p>Paladins who follow the Watchers’ oath are ever vigilant in spotting the influence of extraplanar forces, often establishing a network of spies and informants to gather information on suspected cults. To a Watcher, keeping a healthy suspicion and awareness about one’s surroundings is as natural as wearing armor in battle.</p>
			<h5>TENETS OF THE WATCHERS</h5>
			<p>A paladin who assumes the Oath of the Watchers swears to safeguard mortal realms from otherworldly threats.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Vigilance.</em></strong> The threats you face are cunning, powerful, and subversive. Be ever alert for their corruption.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Loyalty.</em></strong> Never accept gifts or favors from fiends or those who truck with them. Stay true to your order, your comrades, and your duty.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Discipline.</em></strong> You are the shield against the endless terrors that lie beyond the stars. Your blade must be forever sharp and your mind keen to survive what lies beyond.</p>
			<div element="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_OATH_SPELLS" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_CHANNEL_DIVINITY" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_AURA_OF_THE_SENTINEL" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_VIGILANT_REBUKE" />
			<div element="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_MORTAL_BULWARK" />
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You protect the mortal realms from the predations of extraplanar creatures.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_OATH_SPELLS" level="3" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_CHANNEL_DIVINITY" level="3" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_AURA_OF_THE_SENTINEL" level="7" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_VIGILANT_REBUKE" level="15" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_MORTAL_BULWARK" level="20" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Oath Spells" type="Archetype Feature" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_OATH_SPELLS">
		<description>
			<p><em>3rd-level Oath of the Watchers feature</em></p>
			<p>You gain oath spells at the paladin levels listed in the Oath of the Watchers table. See the Sacred Oath class feature for how oath spells work.</p>
			<h5 class="caption">OATH OF THE WATCHERS SPELLS</h5>
			<table>
				<thead>
					<tr><td>Paladin Level</td><td>Spells</td></tr>
				</thead>
				<tr><td>3rd</td><td>alarm, detect magic</td></tr>
				<tr><td>5th</td><td>moonbeam, see invisibility</td></tr>
				<tr><td>9th</td><td>counterspell, nondetection</td></tr>
				<tr><td>13th</td><td>aura of purity, banishment</td></tr>
				<tr><td>17th</td><td>hold monster, scrying</td></tr>
			</table>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_ALARM" level="3" spellcasting="Paladin" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DETECT_MAGIC" level="3" spellcasting="Paladin" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_MOONBEAM" level="5" spellcasting="Paladin" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SEE_INVISIBILITY" level="5" spellcasting="Paladin" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_COUNTERSPELL" level="9" spellcasting="Paladin" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_NONDETECTION" level="9" spellcasting="Paladin" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_AURA_OF_PURITY" level="13" spellcasting="Paladin" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_BANISHMENT" level="13" spellcasting="Paladin" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_HOLD_MONSTER" level="17" spellcasting="Paladin" prepared="true" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SCRYING" level="17" spellcasting="Paladin" prepared="true" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Channel Divinity" type="Archetype Feature" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_CHANNEL_DIVINITY">
		<description>
			<p><em>3rd-level Oath of the Watchers feature</em></p>
			<p>You gain the following Channel Divinity options. See the Sacred Oath class feature for how Channel Divinity works.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Watcher’s Will.</em></strong> You can use your Channel Divinity to invest your presence with the warding power of your faith. As an action, you can choose a number of creatures you can see within 30 feet of you, up to a number equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one creature). For 1 minute, all the chosen creatures have advantage on Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Abjure the Extraplanar.</em></strong> You can use your Channel Divinity to castigate unworldly beings. As an action, you present your holy symbol and each aberration, celestial, elemental, fey, or fiend within 30 feet of you that can hear you must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is turned for 1 minute or until it takes damage.</p>
			<p class="indent">A turned creature must spend its turns trying to move as far away from you as it can, and it can’t willingly move to a space within 30 feet of you. For its action, it can use only the Dash action or try to escape from an effect that prevents it from moving. If there’s nowhere to move, the creature can use the Dodge action.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_CD_WATCHERS_WILL" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_CD_ABJURE_THE_EXTRAPLANAR" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Channel Divinity: Watcher’s Will" type="Archetype Feature" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_CD_WATCHERS_WILL">
		<description>
			<p>You can use your Channel Divinity to invest your presence with the warding power of your faith. As an action, you can choose a number of creatures you can see within 30 feet of you, up to a number equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one creature). For 1 minute, all the chosen creatures have advantage on Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Watcher’s Will" action="Action" usage="Channel Divinity">
			<description>You can choose up to {{watchers will:creatures}} creatures you can see within 30 feet of you. For 1 minute, all the chosen creatures have advantage on Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="watchers will:creatures" value="1" bonus="base" />
			<stat name="watchers will:creatures" value="charisma:modifier" bonus="base" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Channel Divinity: Abjure the Extraplanar" type="Archetype Feature" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_CD_ABJURE_THE_EXTRAPLANAR">
		<description>
			<p>You can use your Channel Divinity to castigate unworldly beings. As an action, you present your holy symbol and each elemental, fey, fiend, or aberration within 30 feet of you that can hear you must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is turned for 1 minute or until it takes damage.</p>
			<p>A turned creature must spend its turns trying to move as far away from you as it can, and it can’t willingly move to a space within 30 feet of you. For its action, it can use only the Dash action or try to escape from an effect that prevents it from moving. If there’s nowhere to move, the creature can use the Dodge action.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Abjure the Extraplanar" action="Action" usage="Channel Divinity">
			<description>You present your holy symbol and each elemental, fey, fiend, or aberration within 30 feet of you that can hear you must make a Wisdom save. On a failed save, the creature is turned for 1 minute or until it takes damage.
			A turned creature must spend its turns trying to move as far away from you as it can, and it can’t willingly move to a space within 30 feet of you. For its action, it can use only the Dash action or try to escape from an effect that prevents it from moving. If there’s nowhere to move, the creature can use the Dodge action.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Aura of the Sentinel" type="Archetype Feature" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_AURA_OF_THE_SENTINEL">
		<description>
			<p><em>7th- and 18th-level Oath of the Watchers feature</em></p>
			<p>You emit an aura of alertness while you aren’t incapacitated. When you and any creature of your choice within 10 feet of you roll initiative, you each gain a bonus to initiative equal to your proficiency bonus.</p>
			<p>At 18th level, the range of this aura increases to 30 feet.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You emit an aura of alertness while you aren’t incapacitated. When you and any creature of your choice within 10 feet of you rolls initiative, you each gain a +{proficiency}} bonus to initiative.</description>
			<description level="18">You emit an aura of alertness while you aren’t incapacitated. When you and any creature of your choice within 30 feet of you rolls initiative, you each gain a +{{proficiency}} bonus to initiative.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Vigilant Rebuke" type="Archetype Feature" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_VIGILANT_REBUKE">
		<description>
			<p><em>15th-level Oath of the Watchers feature</em></p>
			<p>You’ve learned how to chastise anyone who dares wield beguilements against you and your wards. Whenever you or a creature you can see within 30 feet of you succeeds on an Intelligence, Wisdom, or a Charisma saving throw, you can use your reaction to deal 2d8 + your Charisma modifier force damage to the creature that forced the saving throw.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Whenever you or a creature you can see within 30 feet of you succeeds on an Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma saving throw, you can use your reaction to deal 2d8+{{charisma:modifier}} force damage to the creature that forced the saving throw.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Mortal Bulwark" type="Archetype Feature" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WATCHERS_MORTAL_BULWARK">
		<description>
			<p><em>20th-level Oath of the Watchers feature</em></p>
			<p>You manifest a spark of divine power in defense of the mortal realms. As a bonus action, you gain the following benefits for 1 minute:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You gain truesight in a 120-foot radius.</li>
				<li>You have advantage on attack rolls against aberrations, celestials, elementals, fey, and fiends.</li>
				<li>When you hit a creature with an attack roll and deal damage to it, you can also force it to make a Charisma saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the creature is magically banished to its native plane of existence if it’s currently not there. On a successful save, the creature can’t be banished by this feature for 24 hours.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Once you use this bonus action, you can’t use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Bonus Action" usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>You gain the following benefits for 1 minute:
			You gain truesight in a 120-foot radius.
			You have advantage on attack rolls against aberrations, celestials, elementals, fey, and fiends.
			When you hit a creature with an attack and deal damage to it, you can also force it to make a Charisma save. On a failed save, the creature is magically banished to its native plane of existence if it’s currently not there. On a successful save, the creature can’t be banished by this feature for 24 hours.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
</elements>
