<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
  <info>
    <name>Spells</name>
		<description>New Spells and Expanded Class Spell Lists from Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</description>
		<author url="http://dnd.wizards.com/products/tabletop-games/rpg-products/tashas-cauldron-everything">Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</author>
    <update version="0.2.4">
      <file name="spells.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tregolani/wotc-dnd-content/main/tashas-cauldron-everything/spells.xml"/>
    </update>
  </info>

  <element name="Aid" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_AID">
    <supports>Bard, Cleric, Ranger, Paladin, Artificer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Your spell bolsters your allies with toughness and resolve. Choose up to three creatures within range. Each target’s hit point maximum and current hit points increase by 5 for the duration.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, a target’s hit points increase by an additional 5 for each slot level above 2nd.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">8 hours</set>
      <set name="range">30 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a tiny strip of white cloth</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Antipathy/Sympathy" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_ANTIPATHY_SYMPATHY">
    <supports>Bard, Druid, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>This spell attracts or repels creatures of your choice. You target something within range, either a Huge or smaller object or creature or an area that is no larger than a 200-foot cube. Then specify a kind of intelligent creature, such as red dragons, goblins, or vampires. You invest the target with an aura that either attracts or repels the specified creatures for the duration. Choose antipathy or sympathy as the aura’s effect.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>Antipathy.</em></strong> The enchantment causes creatures of the kind you designated to feel an intense urge to leave the area and avoid the target. When such a creature can see the target or comes within 60 feet of it, the creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or become frightened. The creature remains frightened while it can see the target or is within 60 feet of it. While frightened by the target, the creature must use its movement to move to the nearest safe spot from which it can’t see the target. If the creature moves more than 60 feet from the target and can’t see it, the creature is no longer frightened, but the creature becomes frightened again if it regains sight of the target or moves within 60 feet of it.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>Sympathy.</em></strong> The enchantment causes the specified creatures to feel an intense urge to approach the target while within 60 feet of it or able to see it. When such a creature can see the target or comes within 60 feet of it, the creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or use its movement on each of its turns to enter the area or move within reach of the target. When the creature has done so, it can’t willingly move away from the target.</p>
      <p class="indent">If the target damages or otherwise harms an affected creature, the affected creature can make a Wisdom saving throw to end the effect, as described below.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>Ending the Effect.</em></strong> If an affected creature ends its turn while not within 60 feet of the target or able to see it, the creature makes a Wisdom saving throw. On a successful save, the creature is no longer affected by the target and recognizes the feeling of repugnance or attraction as magical. In addition, a creature affected by the spell is allowed another Wisdom saving throw every 24 hours while the spell persists.</p>
      <p class="indent">creature that successfully saves against this effect is immune to it for 1 minute, after which time it can be affected again.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">8</set>
      <set name="school">Enchantment</set>
      <set name="time">1 hour</set>
      <set name="duration">10 days</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">either a lump of alum soaked in vinegar for the antipathy effect or a drop of honey for the sympathy effect</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Augury" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_AUGURY">
    <supports>Cleric, Druid, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>By casting gem-inlaid sticks, rolling dragon bones, laying out ornate cards, or employing some other divining tool, you receive an omen from an otherworldly entity about the results of a specific course of action that you plan to take within the next 30 minutes. The DM chooses from the following possible omens:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Weal, for good results</li>
        <li>Woe, for bad results</li>
        <li>Weal and woe, for both good and bad results</li>
        <li>Nothing, for results that aren’t especially good or bad</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The spell doesn’t take into account any possible circumstances that might change the outcome, such as the casting of additional spells or the loss or gain of a companion.</p>
      <p class="indent">If you cast the spell two or more times before completing your next long rest, there is a cumulative 25 percent chance for each casting after the first that you get a random reading. The DM makes this roll in secret.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Divination</set>
      <set name="time">1 minute</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">Self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">specially marked sticks, bones, or similar tokens worth at least 25 gp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">true</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Aura of Life" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_AURA_OF_LIFE">
    <supports>Cleric,Paladin</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Life-preserving energy radiates from you in an aura with a 30-foot radius. Until the spell ends, the aura moves with you, centered on you. Each non-hostile creature in the aura (including you) has resistance to necrotic damage, and its hit point maximum can’t be reduced. In addition, a non-hostile, living creature regains 1 hit point when it starts its turn in the aura with 0 hit points.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">4</set>
      <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
      <set name="range">Self (30-foot radius)</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>  
  <element name="Aura of Purity" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_AURA_OF_PURITY">
    <supports>Cleric,Paladin</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Purifying energy radiates from you in an aura with a 30-foot radius. Until the spell ends, the aura moves with you, centered on you. Each non-hostile creature in the aura (including you) can’t become diseased, has resistance to poison damage, and has advantage on saving throws against effects that cause any of the following conditions: blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned, and stunned.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">4</set>
      <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
      <set name="range">Self (30-foot radius)</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Aura of Vitality" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_AURA_OF_VITALITY">
    <supports>Cleric, Druid, Paladin</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Healing energy radiates from you in an aura with a 30-foot radius. Until the spell ends, the aura moves with you, centered on you. You can use a bonus action to cause one creature in the aura (including you) to regain 2d6 hit points.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">Self (30-foot radius)</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Bigby’s Hand" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_BIGBYS_HAND">
    <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You create a Large hand of shimmering, translucent force in an unoccupied space that you can see within range. The hand lasts for the spell’s duration, and it moves at your command, mimicking the movements of your own hand. The hand is an object that has AC 20 and hit points equal to your hit point maximum. If it drops to 0 hit points, the spell ends. It has a Strength of 26 (+8) and a Dexterity of 10 (+0). The hand doesn’t fill its space. When you cast the spell and as a bonus action on your subsequent turns, you can move the hand up to 60 feet and then cause one of the following effects with it. Clenched Fist. The hand strikes one creature or object within 5 feet of it. Make a melee spell attack for the hand using your game statistics. On a hit, the target takes 4d8 force damage. Forceful Hand. The hand attempts to push a creature within 5 feet of it in a direction you choose. Make a check with the hand’s Strength contested by the Strength (Athletics) check of the target. If the target is Medium or smaller, you have advantage on the check. If you succeed, the hand pushes the target up to 5 feet plus a number of feet equal to five times your spellcasting ability modifier. The hand moves with the target to remain within 5 feet of it. Grasping Hand. The hand attempts to grapple a Huge or smaller creature within 5 feet of it. You use the hand’s Strength score to resolve the grapple. If the target is Medium or smaller, you have advantage on the check. While the hand is grappling the target, you can use a bonus action to have the hand crush it. When you do so, the target takes bludgeoning damage equal to 2d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier. Interposing Hand. The hand interposes itself between you and a creature you choose until you give the hand a different command. The hand moves to stay between you and the target, providing you with half cover against the target. The target can’t move through the hand’s space if its Strength score is less than or equal to the hand’s Strength score. If its Strength score is higher than the hand’s Strength score, the target can move toward you through the hand’s space, but that space is difficult terrain for the target.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, the damage from the clenched fist option increases by 2d8 and the damage from the grasping hand increases by 2d6 for each slot level above 5th.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">force</set>
      <set name="level">5</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">120 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">an eggshell and a snakeskin glove</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Blade of Disaster" type="Spell" source="Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden" id="ID_IDROTF_SPELL_BLADE_OF_DISASTER">
    <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You create a blade-shaped planar rift about 3 feet long in an unoccupied space you can see within range. The blade lasts for the duration. When you cast this spell, you can make up to two melee spell attacks with the blade, each one against a creature, loose object, or structure within 5 feet of the blade. On a hit, the target takes 4d12 force damage. This attack scores a critical hit if the number on the d20 is 18 or higher. On a critical hit, the blade deals an extra 8d12 force damage (for a total of 12d12 force damage).</p>
      <p class="indent">As a bonus action on your turn, you can move the blade up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space you can see and then make up to two melee spell attacks with it again.</p>
      <p class="indent">The blade can harmlessly pass through any barrier, including a wall of force.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">9</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent"></set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Booming Blade" type="Spell" source="Sword Coast Adventurer’s Guide" id="ID_SCAG_SPELL_BOOMING_BLADE">
    <supports>Artificer, Sorcerer, Wizard, Warlock</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You brandish the weapon used in the spell's casting and make a melee attack with it against one creature within 5 feet of you. On a hit, the target suffers the weapon attack’s normal effects, and then becomes sheathed in booming energy until the start of your next turn. If the target willingly moves 5 feet or more before then, the target takes 1d8 thunder damage, and the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent">This spell’s damage increases when you reach higher levels. At 5th level, the melee attack deals an extra 1d8 thunder damage to the target on a hit, and the damage the target takes for moving increases to 2d8. Both damage rolls increase by 1d8 at 11th level (2d8 and 3d8) and 17th level (3d8 and 4d8).</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">thunder</set>
      <set name="level">0</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">1 round</set>
      <set name="range">Self (5 foot radius)</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a weapon worth at least 1 sp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Color Spray" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_COLOR_SPRAY">
    <supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A dazzling array of flashing, colored light springs from your hand. Roll 6d10, the total is how many hit points of creatures this spell can effect. Creatures in a 15-foot cone originating from you are affected in ascending order of their current hit points (ignoring unconscious creatures and creatures that can’t see).</p>
      <p class="indent">Starting with the creature that has the lowest current hit points, each creature affected by this spell is blinded until the end of your next turn. Subtract each creature’s hit points from the total before moving on to the creature with the next lowest hit points. A creature’s hit points must be equal to or less than the remaining total for the creature to be affected.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, roll an additional 2d10 for each slot level above 1st.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">1</set>
      <set name="school">Illusion</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">1 round</set>
      <set name="range">Self (15-foot cone)</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a pinch of powder or sand that is colored red, yellow, and blue</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Command" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_COMMAND">
    <supports>Bard, Cleric, Paladin</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You speak a one-word command to a creature you can see within range. The target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or follow the command on its next turn. The spell has no effect if the target is undead, if it doesn’t understand your language, or if your command is directly harmful to it.  Some typical commands and their effects follow. You might issue a command other than one described here. If you do so, the DM determines how the target behaves. If the target can’t follow your command, the spell ends.</p>  
      <p class="indent"><b><i>Approach.</i></b> The target moves toward you by the shortest and most direct route, ending its turn if it moves within 5 feet of you.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>Drop.</i></b> The target drops whatever it is holding and then ends its turn.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>Flee.</i></b> The target spends its turn moving away from you by the fastest available means.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>Grovel.</i></b> The target falls prone and then ends its turn.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>Halt.</i></b> The target doesn’t move and takes no actions. A flying creature stays aloft, provided that it is able to do so. If it must move to stay aloft, it flies the minimum distance needed to remain in the air.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, you can affect one additional creature for each slot level above 1st. The creatures must be within 30 feet of each other when you target them.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">1</set>
      <set name="school">Enchantment</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">1 round</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Cone of Cold" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_CONE_OF_COLD">
    <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A blast of cold air erupts from your hands. Each creature in a 60-foot cone must make a Constitution saving throw. A creature takes 8d8 cold damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. A creature killed by this spell becomes a frozen statue until it thaws.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, the damage increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 5th.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">cold</set>
      <set name="level">5</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">Self (60-foot cone)</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a small crystal or glass cone</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Continual Flame" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_CONTINUAL_FLAME">
    <supports>Cleric, Druid, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A flame, equivalent in brightness to a torch, springs forth from an object that you touch. The effect looks like a regular flame, but it creates no heat and doesn’t use oxygen. A continual flame can be covered or hidden but not smothered or quenched.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Until dispelled</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">ruby dust worth 50 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Demiplane" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DEMIPLANE">
    <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You create a shadowy door on a flat solid surface that you can see within range. The door is large enough to allow Medium creatures to pass through unhindered. When opened, the door leads to a demiplane that appears to be an empty room 30 feet in each dimension, made of wood or stone. When the spell ends, the door disappears, and any creatures or objects inside the demiplane remain trapped there, as the door also disappears from the other side. Each time you cast this spell, you can create a new demiplane, or have the shadowy door connect to a demiplane you created with a previous casting of this spell. Additionally, if you know the nature and contents of a demiplane created by a casting of  this spell by another creature, you can have the shadowy door connect to its demiplane instead.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">8</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">1 hour</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Divination" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DIVINATION">
    <supports>Cleric, Druid, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Your magic and an offering put you in contact with a god or a god’s servants. You ask a single question concerning a specific goal, event, or activity to occur within 7 days. The DM offers a truthful reply. The reply might be a short phrase, a cryptic rhyme, or an omen. The spell doesn’t take into account any possible circumstances that might change the outcome, such as the casting of additional spells or the loss or gain of a companion. If you cast this spell two or more times before finishing your next long rest, there is a cumulative 25 percent chance for each casting after the first that you get a random reading. The DM makes this roll in secret.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">4</set>
      <set name="school">Divination</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">Self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">incense and a sacrificial offering appropriate to your religion, together worth at least 25 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">true</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Dominate Beast" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DOMINATE_BEAST">
    <supports>Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You attempt to beguile a beast that you can see within range. It must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or be charmed by you for the duration. If you or creatures that are friendly to you are fighting it, it has advantage on the saving throw. While the beast is charmed, you have a telepathic link with it as long as the two of you are on the same plane of existence. You can use this telepathic link to issue commands to the creature while you are conscious (no action required), which it does its best to obey. You can specify a simple and general course of action, such as “Attack that creature,” “Run over there,” or “Fetch that object.” If the creature completes the order and doesn’t receive further direction from you, it defends and preserves itself to the best of its ability. You can use your action to take total and precise control of the target. Until the end of your next turn, the creature takes only the actions you choose, and doesn’t do anything that you don’t allow it to do. During this time, you can also cause the creature to use a reaction, but this requires you to use your own reaction as well. Each time the target takes damage, it makes a new Wisdom saving throw against the spell. If the saving throw succeeds, the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell with a 5th-level spell slot, the duration is concentration, up to 10 minutes. When you use a 6th-level spell slot, the duration is concentration, up to  1 hour. When you use a spell slot of 7th level or higher, the duration is concentration, up to 8 hours.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">4</set>
      <set name="school">Enchantment</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Dream of the Blue Veil" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_DREAM_OF_THE_BLUE_VEIL">
    <supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You and up to eight willing creatures within range fall unconscious for the spell's duration and expeience visions of another world on the Material Plane such as Oerth, Toril, Krynn, or Eberron. If the spell reaches its full duration, the visions conclude with each of you encountering and pulling back a mystic blue curtain. The spell then ends with you mentally and physically transported to the world that was in the visions.</p>
	  <p class="indent">To cast this spell, you must have a magic item that originated on the world you with to reach, and you must be aware of the world's existence even if you don't know the world's name. Your destination in the other world is a safe location within 1 mile of where the magic item was created. Alternatively, you can cast the spell if one of the affected creatures was born on the other world, which causes your destination to be a safe location within 1 mile of where that creature was born.</p>
	  <p class="indent">The spell ends early on acreature if that creature takes any damage, and the creature isn't transported. If you take any damage, the spell ends for you and all the other creatures, with none of you being transported.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">7</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">10 minutes</set>
      <set name="duration">6 hours</set>
      <set name="range">20 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a magic item or a willing creature fromthe destination world</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Elemental Weapon" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_ELEMENTAL_WEAPON">
    <supports>Druid, Ranger, Paladin, Artificer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A nonmagical weapon you touch becomes a magic weapon. Choose one of the following damage types: acid, cold, fire, lightning, or thunder. For the duration, the weapon has a +1 bonus to attack rolls and deals an extra 1d4 damage of the chosen type when it hits.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th or 6th level, the bonus to attack rolls increases to +2 and the extra damage increases to 2d4. When you use a spell slot of 7th level or higher, the bonus increases to +3 and the extra damage increases to 3d4.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">acid,cold,fire,lightning,thunder</set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Enhance Ability" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_ENHANCE_ABILITY">
    <supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You touch a creature and bestow upon it a magical enhancement. Choose one of the following effects: the target gains the effect until the spell ends.</p>
    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Bear’s Endurance.</em></strong> The target has advantage on Constitution checks. It also gains 2d6 temporary hit points, which are lost when the spell ends.</p>
    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Bull’s Strength.</em></strong> The target has advantage on Strength checks, and his or her carrying capacity doubles.</p>
    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Cat’s Grace.</em></strong> The target has advantage on Dexterity checks. It also doesn’t take damage from falling 20 feet or less if it isn’t incapacitated.</p>
    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Eagle’s Splendor.</em></strong> The target has advantage on Charisma checks.</p>
    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Fox’s Cunning.</em></strong> The target has advantage on Intelligence checks.</p>
    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Owl’s Wisdom.</em></strong> The target has advantage on Wisdom checks.</p>
    <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, you can target one additional creature for each slot level above 2nd.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">fur or a feather from a beast</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Enlarge/Reduce" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_ENLARGE_REDUCE">
    <supports>Bard, Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You cause a creature or an object you can see within range to grow larger or smaller for the duration. Choose either a creature or an object that is neither worn nor carried. If the target is unwilling, it can make a Constitution saving throw. On a success, the spell has no effect.</p>
      <p class="indent">If the target is a creature, everything it is wearing and carrying changes size with it. Any item dropped by an affected creature returns to normal size at once.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>Enlarge.</em></strong> The target’s size doubles in all dimensions, and its weight is multiplied by eight. This growth increases its size by one category - from Medium to Large, for example. If there isn’t enough room for the target to double its size, the creature or object attains the maximum possible size in the space available. Until the spell ends, the target also has advantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws. The target’s weapons also grow to match its new size. While these weapons are enlarged, the target’s attack with them deal 1d4 extra damage.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>Reduce.</em></strong> The target’s size is halved in all dimensions, and its weight is reduced to one-eighth of normal. This reduction decreases its size by one category - from Medium to Small, for example. Until the spell ends, the target also has disadvantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws. The target’s weapons also shrink to match its new size. While these weapons are reduced, the target’s attacks with them deal 1d4 less damage (this can’t reduce the damage below 1).</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">30 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a pinch of powdered iron</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Entangle" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_ENTANGLE">
    <supports>Druid, Ranger</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Grasping weeds and vines sprout from the ground in a 20-foot square starting from a point within range. For the duration, these plants turn the ground in the area into difficult terrain. A creature in the area when you cast the spell must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be restrained by the entangling plants until the spell ends. A creature restrained by the plants can use its action to make a Strength check against your spell save DC. On a success, it frees itself. When the spell ends, the conjured plants wilt away.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">1</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">90 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Fire Shield" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FIRE_SHIELD">
    <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Thin and wispy flames wreathe your body for the duration, shedding bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet, You can end the spell early by using an action to dismiss it. The flames provide you with a warm shield or a chill shield, as you choose. The warm shield grants you resistance to cold damage, and the chill shield grants you resistance to fire damage. In addition, whenever a creature within 5 feet of you hits you with a melee attack, the shield erupts with flame. The attacker takes 2d8 fire damage from a warm shield, or 2d8 cold damage from a cold shield.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">fire,cold</set>
      <set name="level">4</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">10 minutes</set>
      <set name="range">Self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a bit of phosphorous or a firefly</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Flame Blade" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FLAME_BLADE">
    <supports>Druid, Sorcerer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You evoke a fiery blade in your free hand. The blade is similar in size and shape to a scimitar, and it lasts for the duration. If you let go of the blade, it disappears, but you can evoke the blade again as a bonus action. You can use your action to make a melee spell attack with the fiery blade. On a hit, the target takes 3d6 fire damage. The flaming blade sheds bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the damage increases by 1d6 for every two slot levels above 2nd.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">fire</set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
      <set name="range">Self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">leaf of sumac</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Flaming Sphere" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FLAMING_SPHERE">
    <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A 5-foot-diameter sphere of fire appears in an unoccupied space of your choice within range and lasts for the duration. Any creature that ends its turn within 5 feet of the sphere must make a Dexterity saving throw. The creature takes 2d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. As a bonus action, you can move the sphere up to 30 feet. If you ram the sphere into a creature, that creature must make the saving throw against the sphere’s damage, and the sphere stops moving this turn. When you move the sphere, you can direct it over barriers up to 5 feet tall and jump it across pits up to 10 feet wide. The sphere ignites flammable objects not being worn or carried, and it sheds bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the damage increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 2nd.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">fire</set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a bit of tallow, a pinch of brimstone, and a dusting of powdered iron</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Flesh to Stone" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FLESH_TO_STONE">
    <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You attempt to turn one creature that you can see within range into stone. If the targets body is made of flesh, the creature must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, it is restrained as its flesh begins to harden. On a successful save, the creature isn’t affected. A creature restrained by this spell must make another Constitution saving throw at the end of each of its turns. If it successfully saves against this spell three times, the spell ends. If it fails saves three times, it is turned to stone and subjected to the petrified condition for the duration. The successes and failures don’t need to be consecutive</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">6</set>
      <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a pinch of lime, water, and earth</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Frostbite" type="Spell" source="Xanathar’s Guide to Everything" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_FROSTBITE">
      <supports>Artificer, Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Rogue (Arcane Trickster), Fighter (Eldritch Knight)</supports>
      <description>
          <p>You cause numbing frost to form on one creature that you can see within range. The target must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 1d6 cold damage, and it has disadvantage on the next weapon attack roll it makes before the end of its next turn.</p>
          <p class="indent">The spell’s damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</p>
      </description>
      <setters>
          <set name="keywords">cold</set>
          <set name="level">0</set>
          <set name="school">Evocation</set>
          <set name="time">1 action</set>
          <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
          <set name="range">60 feet</set>
          <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
          <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
          <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
          <set name="materialComponent"></set>
          <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
          <set name="isRitual">false</set>
      </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Gate" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_GATE">
    <supports>Cleric, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You conjure a portal linking an unoccupied space you can see within range to a precise location on a different plane of existence. The portal is a circular opening, which you can make 5 to 20 feet in diameter. You can orient the portal in any direction you choose. The portal lasts for the duration. The portal has a front and a back on each plane where it appears. Travel through the portal is possible only by moving through its front. Anything that does so is instantly transported to the other plane, appearing in the unoccupied space nearest to the portal. Deities and other planar rulers can prevent portals created by this spell from opening in their presence or anywhere within their domains. When you cast this spell, you can speak the name of a specific creature (a pseudonym, title, or nickname doesn’t work). If that creature is on a plane other than the one you are on, the portal opens in the named creature’s immediate vicinity and draws the creature through it to the nearest unoccupied space on your side of the portal. You gain no special power over the creature, and it is free to act as the DM deems appropriate. It might leave, attack you, or help you.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">9</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a diamond worth at least 5,000 gp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Gentle Repose" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_GENTLE_REPOSE">
    <supports>Cleric, Paladin, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You touch a corpse or other remains. For the duration, the target is protected from decay and can’t become undead. The spell also effectively extends the time limit on raising the target from the dead, since days spent under the influence of this spell don’t count against the time limit of spells such as raise dead.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">10 days</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a pinch of salt and one copper piece placed on each of the corpse’s eyes, which must remain there for the duration</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">true</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Grease" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_GREASE">
    <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Slick grease covers the ground in a 10-foot square centered on a point within range and turns it into difficult terrain for the duration. When the grease appears, each creature standing in its area must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or fall prone. A creature that enters the area or ends its turn there must also succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or fall prone.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">1</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a bit of pork rind or butter</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Green-Flame Blade" type="Spell" source="Sword Coast Adventurer’s Guide" id="ID_SCAG_SPELL_GREEN_FLAME_BLADE">
    <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard, Warlock</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You brandish the weapon used in the spell's casting and make a melee attack with it against one creature within 5 feet of you. On a hit, the target suffers the weapon attack’s normal effects, and you can cause green fire to leap from the target to a different creature of your choice that you can see within 5 feet of it. The second creature takes fire damage equal to your spellcasting ability modifier.</p>
      <p class="indent">This spell’s damage increases when you reach higher levels. At 5th level, the melee attack deals an extra 1d8 fire damage to the target on a hit, and the fire damage to the second creature increases to 1d8 + your spellcasting ability modifier. Both damage rolls increase by 1d8 at 11th level (2d8 and 2d8) and 17th level (3d8 and 3d8).</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">fire</set>
      <set name="level">0</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">Self (5 foot radius)</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a weapon worth at least 1 sp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Gust of Wind" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_GUST_OF_WIND">
    <supports>Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A line of strong wind 60 feet long and 10 feet wide blasts from you in a direction you choose for the spell’s duration. Each creature that starts its turn in the line must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be pushed 15 feet away from you in a direction following the line.</p>
      <p class="indent">Any creature in the line must spend 2 feet of movement for every 1 foot it moves when moving closer to you.</p>
      <p class="indent">The gust disperses gas or vapor, and it extinguishes candles, torches, and similar unprotected flames in the area. It causes protected flames, such as those of lanterns, to dance wildly and has a 50 percent chance to extinguish them.</p>
      <p class="indent">As a bonus action on each of your turns before the spell ends, you can change the direction in which the line blasts from you.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">Self (60-foot line)</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a legume seed</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Greater Restoration" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_GREATER_RESTORATION">
    <supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Ranger, Artificer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You imbue a creature you touch with positive energy to undo a debilitating effect. You can reduce the target’s exhaustion level by one, or end one of the following effects on the target:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>One effect that charmed or petrified the target</li>
      <li>One curse, including the target’s attunement to a cursed magic item</li>
      <li>Any reduction to one of the target’s ability scores</li>
      <li>One effect reducing the target’s hit point maximum</li>
    </ul>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">5</set>
      <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">diamond dust worth 100 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Heroes’ Feast" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_HEROES_FEAST">
    <supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You bring forth a great feast, including magnificent food and drink. The feast takes 1 hour to consume and disappears at the end of that time, and the beneficial effects don’t set in until this hour is over. Up to twelve creatures can partake of the feast. A creature that partakes of the feast gains several benefits. The creature is cured of all diseases and poison, becomes immune to poison and being frightened, and makes all Wisdom saving throws with advantage. Its hit point maximum also increases by 2d10, and it gains the same number of hit points. These benefits last for 24 hours.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">6</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">10 minutes</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">30 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a gem-encrusted bowl worth at least 1,000 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Incendiary Cloud" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_INCENDIARY_CLOUD">
    <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A swirling cloud of smoke shot through with white-hot embers appears in a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on a point within range. The cloud spreads around corners and is heavily obscured. It lasts for the duration or until a wind of moderate or greater speed (at least 10 miles per hour) disperses it. When the cloud appears, each creature in it must make a Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 10d8 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. A creature must also make this saving throw when it enters the spell’s area for the first time on a turn or ends its turn there. The cloud moves 10 feet directly away from you in a direction that you choose at the start of each of your turns.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">fire</set>
      <set name="level">8</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">150 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Intellect Fortress" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_INTELLECT_FORTRESS">
    <supports>Artificer, Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>For the duration, you or one willing creature you can see within range has resistance to psychic damage, as well as advantage on Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, you can target one additional creature for each slot level above 3rd. The creatures must be within 30 feet of each other when you target them.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">psychic</set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="range">30 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent"></set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
	<element name="Lightning Lure" type="Spell" source="Sword Coast Adventurer’s Guide" id="ID_SCAG_SPELL_LIGHTNING_LURE">
		<supports>Artificer, Sorcerer, Wizard, Warlock</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You create a lash of lightning energy that strikes at one creature of your choice that you can see within 15 feet of you. The target must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be pulled up to 10 feet in a straight line toward you and then take 1d8 lightning damage if it is within 5 feet of you.</p>
			<p class="indent">This spell’s damage increases by 1d8 when you reach 5th level (2d8), 11th level (3d8), and 17th level (4d8).</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords">lightning</set>
			<set name="level">0</set>
			<set name="school">Evocation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">Self (15 foot radius)</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
  <element name="Magic Weapon" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_MAGIC_WEAPON">
    <supports>Ranger, Paladin, Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You touch a nonmagical weapon. Until the spell ends, that weapon becomes a magic weapon with a +1 bonus to attack rolls and damage rolls.  </p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the bonus increases to +2. When you use a spell slot of 6th level or higher, the bonus increases to +3.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
      <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Mass Healing Word" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_MASS_HEALING_WORD">
    <supports>Bard, Cleric</supports>
    <description>
      <p>As you call out words of restoration, up to six creatures of your choice that you can see within range regain hit points equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting ability modifier. This spell has no effect on undead or constructs.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the healing increases by 1d4 for each slot level above 3rd.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Meld into Stone" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_MELD_INTO_STONE">
    <supports>Cleric, Druid, Ranger</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You step into a stone object or surface large enough to fully contain your body, melding yourself and all the equipment you carry with the stone for the duration. Using your movement, you step into the stone at a point you can touch. Nothing of your presence remains visible or otherwise detectable by nonmagical senses. While merged with the stone, you can’t see what occurs outside it, and any Wisdom (Perception) checks you make to hear sounds outside it are made with disadvantage. You remain aware of the passage of time and can cast spells on yourself while merged in the stone. You can use your movement to leave the stone where you entered it, which ends the spell. You otherwise can’t move. Minor physical damage to the stone doesn’t harm you, but its partial destruction or a change in its shape (to the extent that you no longer fit within it) expels you and deals 6d6 bludgeoning damage to you. The stone’s complete destruction (or transmutation into a different substance) expels you and deals 50 bludgeoning damage to you. If expelled, you fall prone in an unoccupied space closest to where you first entered.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">8 hours</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">true</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Mind Sliver" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_MIND_SLIVER">
    <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You drive a disorienting spike of psychic energy into the mind of one creature you can see within range. The target must succeed on an Intelligence saving throw or take 1d6 psychic damage, and subtract 1d4 from the next saving throw it makes before the end of your next turn.</p>
      <p class="indent">This spell’s damage increases by 1d6 when you reach certain levels: 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">psychic</set>
      <set name="level">0</set>
      <set name="school">Enchantment</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">1 round</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent"></set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Mirror Image" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_MIRROR_IMAGE">
    <supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Three illusory duplicates of yourself appear in your space. Until the spell ends, the duplicates move with you and mimic your actions, shifting position so it’s impossible to track which image is real. You can use your action to dismiss the illusory duplicates. Each time a creature targets you with an attack during the spell’s duration, roll a d20 to determine whether the attack instead targets one of your duplicates. If you have three duplicates, you must roll a 6 or higher to change the attack’s target to a duplicate. With two duplicates, you must roll an 8 or higher. With one duplicate, you must roll an 11 or higher. A duplicate’s AC equals 10 + your Dexterity modifier. If an attack hits a duplicate, the duplicate is destroyed. A duplicate can be destroyed only by an attack that hits it. It ignores all other damage and effects. The spell ends when all three duplicates are destroyed. A creature is unaffected by this spell if it can’t see, if it relies on senses other than sight, such as blindsight, or if it can perceive illusions as false, as with truesight.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Illusion</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">Self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Mislead" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_MISLEAD">
    <supports>Bard, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You become invisible at the same time that an illusory double of you appears where you are standing. The double lasts for the duration, but the invisibility ends if you attack or cast a spell. You can use your action to move your illusory double up to twice your speed and make it gesture, speak, and behave in whatever way you choose. You can see through its eyes and hear through its ears as if you were located where it is. On each of your turns as a bonus action, you can switch from using its senses to using your own, or back again. While you are using its senses, you are blinded and deafened in regard to your own surroundings.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">5</set>
      <set name="school">Illusion</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="range">Self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Otiluke’s Freezing Sphere" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_OTILUKES_FREEZING_SPHERE">
    <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A frigid globe of cold energy streaks from your fingertips to a point of your choice within range, where it explodes in a 60-foot-radius sphere. Each creature within the area must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 10d6 cold damage. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage. If the globe strikes a body of water or a liquid that is principally water (not including water-based creatures), it freezes the liquid to a depth of 6 inches over an area 30 feet square. This ice lasts for 1 minute. Creatures that were swimming on the surface of frozen water are trapped in the ice. A trapped creature can use an action to make a Strength check against your spell save DC to break free. You can refrain from firing the globe after completing the spell, if you wish. A small globe about the size of a sling stone, cool to the touch, appears in your hand. At any time, you or a creature you give the globe to can throw the globe (to a range of 40 feet) or hurl it with a sling (to the sling’s normal range). It shatters on impact, with the same effect as the normal casting of the spell. You can also set the globe down without shattering it. After 1 minute, if the globe hasn’t already shattered, it explodes.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 7th level or higher, the damage increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 6th
      </p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">cold</set>
      <set name="level">6</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">300 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a small crystal sphere</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Phantasmal Killer" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_PHANTASMAL_KILLER">
    <supports>Bard, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You tap into the nightmares of a creature you can see within range and create an illusory manifestation of its deepest fears, visible only to that creature. The target must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the target becomes frightened for the duration. At the end of each of the target’s turns before the spell ends, the target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or take 4d10 psychic damage. On a successful save, the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the damage increases by 1d10 for each slot level above 4th.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">psychic</set>
      <set name="level">4</set>
      <set name="school">Illusion</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">120 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Planar Binding" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_PLANAR_BINDING">
    <supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>With this spell, you attempt to bind a celestial, an elemental, a fey, or a fiend to your service. The creature must be within range for the entire casting of the spell. (Typically, the creature is first summoned into the center of an inverted magic circle in order to keep it trapped while this spell is cast.) At the completion of the casting, the target must make a Charisma saving throw. On a failed save, it is bound to serve you for the duration. If the creature was summoned or created by another spell, that spell’s duration is extended to match the duration of this spell. A bound creature must follow your instructions to the best of its ability. You might command the creature to accompany you on an adventure, to guard a location, or to deliver a message. The creature obeys the letter of your instructions, but if the creature is hostile to you, it strives to twist your words to achieve its own objectives. If the creature carries out your instructions completely before the spell ends, it travels to you to report this fact if you are on the same plane of existence. If you are on a different plane of existence, it returns to the place where you bound it and remains there until the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of a higher level, the duration increases to 10 days with a 6th-level slot, to 30 days with a 7th-level slot, to 180 days with an 8th-level slot, and to a year and a day with a 9th-level spell slot.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">5</set>
      <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 hour</set>
      <set name="duration">24 hours</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a jewel worth at least 1,000 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Power Word Heal" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_POWER_WORD_HEAL">
    <supports>Cleric,Bard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A wave of healing energy washes over the creature you touch. The target regains all its hit points. If the creature is charmed, frightened, paralyzed, or stunned, the condition ends. If the creature is prone, it can use its reaction to stand up. This spell has no effect on undead or constructs.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">9</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Prayer of Healing" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_PRAYER_OF_HEALING">
    <supports>Cleric, Paladin</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Up to six creatures of your choice that you can see within range each regain hit points equal to 2d8 + your spellcasting ability modifier. This spell has no effect on undead or constructs.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the healing increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 2nd.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">10 minutes</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">30 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Prismatic Spray" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_PRISMATIC_SPRAY">
    <supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Eight multicolored rays of light flash from your hand. Each ray is a different color and has a different power and purpose. Each creature in a 60-foot cone must make a Dexterity saving throw. For each target, roll a d8 to determine which color ray affects it.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>1. Red.</i></b>The target takes 10d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>2. Orange.</i></b>The target takes 10d6 acid damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>3. Yellow.</i></b>The target takes 10d6 lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>4. Green.</i></b>The target takes 10d6 poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>5. Blue.</i></b>The target takes 10d6 cold damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>6. Indigo.</i></b>On a failed save, the target is restrained. It must then make a Constitution saving throw at the end of each of its turns. If it successfully saves three times, the spell ends. If it fails its save three times, it permanently turns to stone and is subjected to the petrified condition. The successes and failures don’t need to be consecutive; keep track of both until the target collects three of a kind.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>7. Violet.</i></b>On a failed save, the target is blinded. It must then make a Wisdom saving throw at the start of your next turn. A successful save ends the blindness. If it fails that save, the creature is transported to another plane of existence of the DM’s choosing and is no longer blinded. (Typically, a creature that is on a plane that isn’t its home plane is banished home, while other creatures are usually cast into the Astral or Ethereal planes.)</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>8. Special.</i></b>The target is struck by two rays. Roll twice more, rerolling any 8.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">fire, acid, lightning, poison, cold</set>
      <set name="level">7</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">Self (60 foot cone)</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Prismatic Wall" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_PRISMATIC_WALL">
    <supports>Bard, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A shimmering, multicolored plane of light forms a vertical opaque wall—up to 90 feet long, 30 feet high, and 1 inch thick—centered on a point you can see within range. Alternatively, you can shape the wall into a sphere up to 30 feet in diameter centered on a point you choose within range. The wall remains in place for the duration. If you position the wall so that it passes through a space occupied by a creature, the spell fails, and your action and the spell slot are wasted.</p>
      <p class="indent">The wall sheds bright light out to a range of 100 feet and dim light for an additional 100 feet. You and creatures you designate at the time you cast the spell can pass through and remain near the wall without harm. If another creature that can see the wall moves to within 20 feet of it or starts its turn there, the creature must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or become blinded for 1 minute.</p>
      <p class="indent">The wall consists of seven layers, each with a different color. When a creature attempts to reach into or pass through the wall, it does so one layer at a time through all the wall’s layers. As it passes or reaches through each layer, the creature must make a Dexterity saving throw or be affected by that layer’s properties as described below.</p>
      <p class="indent">The wall can be destroyed, also one layer at a time, in order from red to violet, by means specific to each layer. Once a layer is destroyed, it remains so for the duration of the spell. Antimagic field has no effect on the wall, and dispel magic can affect only the violet layer.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>1. Red.</i></b>The creature takes 10d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. While this layer is in place, nonmagical ranged attacks can’t pass through the wall. The layer can be destroyed by dealing at least 25 cold damage to it.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>2. Orange.</i></b>The creature takes 10d6 acid damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. While this layer is in place, magical ranged attacks can’t pass through the wall. The layer is destroyed by a strong wind.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>3. Yellow.</i></b>The creature takes 10d6 lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. This layer can be destroyed by dealing at least 60 force damage to it.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>4. Green.</i></b>The creature takes 10d6 poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. A passwall spell, or another spell of equal or greater level that can open a portal on a solid surface, destroys this layer.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>5. Blue.</i></b>The creature takes 10d6 cold damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. This layer can be destroyed by dealing at least 25 fire damage to it.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>6. Indigo.</i></b>On a failed save, the creature is restrained. It must then make a Constitution saving throw at the end of each of its turns. If it successfully saves three times, the spell ends. If it fails its save three times, it permanently turns to stone and is subjected to the petrified condition. The successes and failures don’t need to be consecutive; keep track of both until the creature collects three of a kind.</p>
      <p class="indent">While this layer is in place, spells can’t be cast through the wall. The layer is destroyed by bright light shed by a daylight spell or a similar spell of equal or higher level.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>7. Violet.</i></b>On a failed save, the creature is blinded. It must then make a Wisdom saving throw at the start of your next turn. A successful save ends the blindness. If it fails that save, the creature is transported to another plane of the DM’s choosing and is no longer blinded. (Typically, a creature that is on a plane that isn’t its home plane is banished home, while other creatures are usually cast into the Astral or Ethereal planes.) This layer is destroyed by a dispel magic spell or a similar spell of equal or higher level that can end spells and magical effects.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">fire, acid, lightning, poison, cold</set>
      <set name="level">9</set>
      <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">10 minutes</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Protection from Evil and Good" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_PROTECTION_FROM_EVIL_AND_GOOD">
    <supports>Cleric, Druid, Paladin, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Until the spell ends, one willing creature you touch is protected against certain types of creatures: aberrations, celestials, elementals, fey, fiends, and undead. The protection grants several benefits. Creatures of those types have disadvantage on attack rolls against the target. The target also can’t be charmed, frightened, or possessed by them. If the target is already charmed, frightened, or possessed by such a creature, the target has advantage on any new saving throw against the relevant effect.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">1</set>
      <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">holy water or powdered silver and iron, which the spell consumes</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Rary's Telepathic Bond" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_RARYS_TELEPATHIC_BOND">
    <supports>Bard, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You forge a telepathic link among up to eight willing creatures of your choice within range, psychically linking each creature to all the others for the duration. Creatures with Intelligence scores of 2 or less aren’t affected by this spell. Until the spell ends, the targets can communicated telepathically through the bond whether or not they have a common language. The communication is possible over any distance, though it can’t extend to other planes of existence.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">5</set>
      <set name="school">Divination</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">1 hour</set>
      <set name="range">30 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">pieces of eggshell from two different kinds of creatures</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">true</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Revivify" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_REVIVIFY">
    <supports>Cleric, Druid, Ranger, Paladin, Artificer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You touch a creature that has died within the last minute. That creature returns to life with 1 hit point. This spell can’t return to life a creature that has died of old age, nor can it restore any missing body parts.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">diamonds worth 300 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Searing Smite" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SEARING_SMITE">
    <supports>Ranger,Paladin</supports>
    <description>
      <p>The next time you hit a creature with a melee weapon attack during the spell’s duration, your weapon flares with white-hot intensity, and the attack deals an extra 1d6 fire damage to the target and causes the target to ignite in flames. At the start of each of its turns until the spell ends, the target must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, it takes 1d6 fire damage. On a successful save, the spells ends. If the target or a creature within 5 feet of it uses an action to put out the flames, or if some other effect douses the flames (such as the target being submerged in water), the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the initial extra damage dealt by the attack increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 1st.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">fire</set>
      <set name="level">1</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">Self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Slow" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SLOW">
    <supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You alter time around up to six creatures of your choice in a 40-foot cube within range. Each target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or be affected by this spell for the duration.</p>
      <p class="indent">An affected target’s speed is halved, it takes a -2 penalty to AC and Dexterity saving throws, and it can’t use reactions. On its turn, it can use either an action or a bonus action, not both. Regardless of the creature’s abilities or magic items, it can’t make more than one melee or ranged attack during its turn.</p>
      <p class="indent">If the creature attempts to cast a spell with a casting time of 1 action, roll a d20. On an 11 or higher, the spell doesn’t take effect until the creature’s next turn, and the creature must use its action on that turn to complete the spell. If it can’t, the spell is wasted.</p>
      <p class="indent">A creature affected by this spell makes another Wisdom saving throw at the end of each of its turns. On a successful save, the effect ends for it.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">120 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a drop of molasses</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Speak with Dead" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SPEAK_WITH_DEAD">
    <supports>Bard, Cleric, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You grant the semblance of life and intelligence to a corpse of your choice within range, allowing it to answer the questions you pose. The corpse must still have a mouth and can’t be undead. The spell fails if the corpse was the target of this spell within the last 10 days. Until the spell ends, you can ask the corpse up to five questions. The corpse knows only what it knew in life, including the languages it knew. Answers are usually brief, cryptic, or repetitive, and the corpse is under no compulsion to offer a truthful answer if you are hostile to it or it recognizes you as an enemy. This spell doesn’t return the creature’s soul to its body, only its animating spirit. Thus, the corpse can’t learn new information, doesn’t comprehend anything that has happened since it died, and can’t speculate about future events.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">10 minutes</set>
      <set name="range">10 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">burning incense</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Spirit Shroud" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_SPIRIT_SHROUD">
    <supports>Cleric, Paladin, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You call forth spirits of the dead, which flit around you for the spell’s duration. The spirits are intangible and invulnerable.</p>
      <p class="indent">Until the spell ends, any attack you make deals 1d8 extra damage when you hit a creature within 10 feet of you. This damage is radiant, necrotic, or cold (your choice when you cast the spell). Any creature that takes this damage can’t regain hit points until the start of your next turn.</p>
      <p class="indent">In addition, any creature of your choice that you can see that starts its turn within 10 feet of you has its speed reduced by 10 feet until the start of your next turn.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the extra damage increases by 1d8 for every two slot levels above the 3rd.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">radiant,necrotic,cold</set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
      <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
      <set name="range">90 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent"></set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>  
  <element name="Summon Aberration" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_SUMMON_ABERRATION">
    <supports>Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You call forth an aberrant spirit. It manifests in an unoccupied space that you can see within range. This corporeal form uses the Aberrant Spirit stat block. When you cast the spell, choose Beholderkin, Slaad, or Star Spawn. The creature resembles an aberration of that kind, which determines certain traits in its stat block. The creature disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent">The creature is an ally to you and your companions for the spell’s duration. In combat, the creature shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It obeys verbal commands that you issue to it (no action required by you). If you don’t issue any, it takes the Dodge action and uses its move to avoid danger.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the creature assumes the higher level for that casting wherever it uses the spell’s level in its stat block.</p>
      <div class="reference">
        <div element="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_ABERRATION_STATBLOCK" />
      </div>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">4</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="range">90 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a pickled tentacle and an eyeball in a crystal vial worth at least 400 gp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Summon Beast" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_SUMMON_BEAST">
    <supports>Druid, Ranger</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You call forth a bestial spirit. It manifests in an unoccupied space that you can see within range. This corporeal form uses the Bestial Spirit stat block. When you cast the spell, choose an environment: Air, Land, or Water. The creature resembles an animal of your choice that is native to the chosen environment, which determines certain traits in its stat block. The creature disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent">The creature is an ally to you and your companions for the spell’s duration. In combat, the creature shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It obeys verbal commands that you issue to it (no action required by you). If you don’t issue any, it takes the Dodge action and uses its move to avoid danger.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the creature assumes the higher level for that casting wherever it uses the spell’s level in its stat block.</p>
      <div class="reference">
        <div element="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_BEAST_STATBLOCK" />
      </div>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="range">90 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a feather, tuft of fur, and fish tail inside a gilded acorn worth at least 200 gp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Summon Celestial" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_SUMMON_CELESTIAL">
    <supports>Cleric, Paladin</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You call forth an celestial spirit. It manifests in an angelic form in an unoccupied space that you can see within range. This corporeal form uses the Celestial Spirit stat block. When you cast the spell, choose Avenger or Defender. Your choice determines the creature's attack in its stat block. The creature disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent">The creature is an ally to you and your companions for the spell’s duration. In combat, the creature shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It obeys verbal commands that you issue to it (no action required by you). If you don’t issue any, it takes the Dodge action and uses its move to avoid danger.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, the creature assumes the higher level for that casting wherever it uses the spell’s level in its stat block.</p>
      <div class="reference">
        <div element="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_CELESTIAL_STATBLOCK" />
      </div>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">5</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="range">90 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a golden reliquary worth at least 500 gp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Summon Construct" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_SUMMON_CONSTRUCT">
    <supports>Wizard, Artificer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You call forth the spirit of a construct. It manifests in an unoccupied space that yo ucan see within range. This corporeal form uses the Construct Spirit stat block. When you cast the spell, choose a material: Clay, Metal, or Stone. The creature resembles a golem or modron (your choice) made of the chosen material, which determines certain traits in its stat block. The creature disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent">The creature is an ally to you and your companions. In combat, the creature shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It obeys your verbal commands (no action required by you). If you don't issue any, it takes the Dodge actin and uses its move to avoid danger.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, use the higher level wherever the spell's level appears in the stat block.</p>
      <div class="reference">
        <div element="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_CONSTRUCT_STATBLOCK" />
      </div>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">4</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="range">90 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">TBD</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Summon Elemental" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_SUMMON_ELEMENTAL">
    <supports>Druid, Ranger, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You call forth an elemental spirit. It manifests in an unoccupied space that you can see within range. This corporeal form uses the Elemental Spirit stat block. When you cast the spell, choose an element: Air, Earth, Fire, or Water. The creature resembles a bipedal form wreathed in the chosen element, which determines certain traits in its stat block. The creature disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent">The creature is an ally to you and your companions for the spell’s duration. In combat, the creature shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It obeys verbal commands that you issue to it (no action required by you). If you don’t issue any, it takes the Dodge action and uses its move to avoid danger.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the creature assumes the higher level for that casting wherever it uses the spell’s level in its stat block.</p>
      <div class="reference">
        <div element="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_ELEMENTAL_STATBLOCK" />
      </div>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">4</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="range">90 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">air, a pebble, ash, and water inside a crystal vial worth at least 400 gp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Summon Fey" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_SUMMON_FEY">
    <supports>Bard, Druid, Ranger, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You call forth a fey spirit. It manifests in an unoccupied space that you can see within range. This corporeal form uses the Fey Spirit stat block. When you cast the spell, choose an mood: Fuming, Mirthful, or Tricksy. The creature resembles a fey creature of your choice marked by the chosen mood, which determines one of the traits in its stat block. The creature disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent">The creature is an ally to you and your companions for the spell’s duration. In combat, the creature shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It obeys verbal commands that you issue to it (no action required by you). If you don’t issue any, it takes the Dodge action and uses its move to avoid danger.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the creature assumes the higher level for that casting wherever it uses the spell’s level in its stat block.</p>
      <div class="reference">
        <div element="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_FEY_STATBLOCK" />
      </div>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="range">90 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a gilded flower worth at least 300 gp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Summon Fiend" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_SUMMON_FIEND">
    <supports>Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
       <p>You call forth a fiendish spirit. It manifests in an unoccupied space that you can see within range. This corporeal form uses the Fiendish Spirit stat block. When you cast the spell, choose Demon, Devil, or Yugoloth. The creature resembles a fiend of the chosen type, which determines certain traits in its stat block. The creature disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent">The creature is an ally to you and your companions for the spell’s duration. In combat, the creature shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It obeys verbal commands that you issue to it (no action required by you). If you don’t issue any, it takes the Dodge action and uses its move to avoid danger.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 7th level or higher, the creature assumes the higher level for that casting wherever it uses the spell’s level in its stat block.</p>
      <div class="reference">
        <div element="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_FIENDISH_SPIRIT_STATBLOCK" />
      </div>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">6</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="range">90 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">humanoid blood inside a ruby vial worth at least 600 gp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Summon Shadowspawn" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_SUMMON_SHADOWSPAWN">
    <supports>Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
       <p>You call forth a shadowy spirit. It manifests in an unoccupied space that you can see within range. This corporeal form uses the Shadow Spirit stat block. When you cast the spell, choose an emotion: Fury, Despair, or Fear. The creature resembles a misshapen biped marked by he chosen emotion, which determines certain traits in its stat block. The creature disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent">The creature is an ally to you and your companions for the spell’s duration. In combat, the creature shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It obeys verbal commands that you issue to it (no action required by you). If you don’t issue any, it takes the Dodge action and uses its move to avoid danger.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the creature assumes the higher level for that casting wherever it uses the spell’s level in its stat block.</p>
      <div class="reference">
        <div element="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_SHADOWSPAWN_STATBLOCK" />
      </div>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="range">90 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">tears inside a gem worth at least 300 gp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Summon Undead" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_SUMMON_UNDEAD">
    <supports>Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
       <p>You call forth an undead spirit. It manifests in an unoccupied space that you can see within range. This corporeal form uses the Undead Spirit stat block. When you cast the spell, choose the creature's form: Ghostly, Putrid, or Skeletal. The spirit resembles an undead creature of the chosen form, which determines certain traits in its stat block. The creature disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
      <p class="indent">The creature is an ally to you and your companions for the spell’s duration. In combat, the creature shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It obeys verbal commands that you issue to it (no action required by you). If you don’t issue any, it takes the Dodge action and uses its move to avoid danger.</p>
      <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the creature assumes the higher level for that casting wherever it uses the spell’s level in its stat block.</p>
      <div class="reference">
        <div element="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_UNDEAD_STATBLOCK" />
      </div>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="range">90 feet</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a gilded humanoid skull worth at least 300 gp</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Sunbeam" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SUNBEAM">
    <supports>Cleric,Druid,Sorcerer,Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A beam of brilliant light flashes out from your hand in a 5-foot-wide, 60-foot-line. Each creature in the line must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 6d8 radiant damage and is blinded until your next turn. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage and isn’t blinded by this spell. Undead and oozes have disadvantage on this saving throw. You can create a new line of radiance as your action on any turn until the spell ends. For the duration, a mote of brilliant radiance shines in your hand. It sheds bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet. The light is sunlight.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">radiant</set>
      <set name="level">6</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">Self (60-foot line)</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a magnifying glass</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Sunburst" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SUNBURST">
    <supports>Cleric,Druid,Sorcerer,Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Brilliant sunlight flashes in a 60-foot radius centered on a point you choose within range. Each creature in that light must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 12d6 radiant damage and is blinded for 1 minute. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage and isn’t blinded by this spell. Undead and oozes have disadvantage on this saving throw.  A creature blinded by this spell makes another Constitution saving throw at the end of each of its turns. On a successful save, it is no longer blinded.  This spell dispels any darkness in its area that was created by a spell.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">radiant</set>
      <set name="level">8</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">150 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">fire and a piece of sunstone</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
	<element name="Sword Burst" type="Spell" source="Sword Coast Adventurer’s Guide" id="ID_SCAG_SPELL_SWORD_BURST">
		<supports>Artificer, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You create a momentary circle of spectral blades that sweep around you. Each creature within range, other than you, must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 1d6 force damage.</p>
			<p class="indent">This spell’s damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords">force</set>
			<set name="level">0</set>
			<set name="school">Conjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">5 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
  <element name="Symbol" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SYMBOL">
    <supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>When you cast this spell, you inscribe a harmful glyph either on a surface (such as a section of floor, a wall, or a table) or within an object that can be closed to conceal the glyph (such as a book, a scroll, or a treasure chest). If you choose a surface, the glyph can cover an area of the surface no larger than 10 feet in diameter. If you choose an object, that object must remain in its place</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">7</set>
      <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 minute</set>
      <set name="duration">Until dispelled or triggered</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">mercury, phosphorus, and powdered diamond and opal with a total value of at least 1,000 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
	<element name="Tasha's Caustic Brew" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Guide to Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_TASHAS_CAUSTIC_BREW">
		<supports>Artificer, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>A stream of acid emanates from you in a line 30 feet long and 5 feet wide in a direction you choose. Each creature in the line must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or be covered in acid for the spell's duration or until a creature uses its action to scrape or wash the acid off itself or another creature. A creature covered in the acid takes 2d4 acid damage at start of each of its turns.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the damage increases by 2d4 for each slot level above 1st.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords">acid</set>
			<set name="level">1</set>
			<set name="school">Evocation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
			<set name="range">Self (30 foot line)</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a bit of rotten food</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Tasha's Mind Whip" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Guide to Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_TASHAS_MIND_WHIP">
		<supports>Artificer, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You psychically lash out at one creature you can see within range. The target must make an Intelligence saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 3d6 psychic damage, and it can't take a reaction until the end of its next turn. Moreover, on its next turn, it must choose whether it gets a move, an action, or a bonus action; it gets only one of the three. On a successful save, the target takes half as much damage and suffers none of the spell's other effects.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, you can target one additional creature for each slot level above 2nd. The creatures must be within 30 feet of each other when you target them.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords">psychic</set>
			<set name="level">1</set>
			<set name="school">Enchantment</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">1 round</set>
			<set name="range">90 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent"/>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Tasha's Otherworldly Guise" type="Spell" source="Tasha's Guide to Everything" id="ID_TCOE_SPELL_TASHAS_OTHERWORLDLY_GUISE">
		<supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Uttering an incantation, you draw on the magic of the Lower Planes or Upper Planes (your choice) to transform yourself. You gain the following benefits until the spell ends:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You are immune to fire and poison damage (Lower Planes) or radiant and necrotic damage (Upper Planes).</li>
				<li>You are immune to the poisoned condition (Lower Planes) or the charmed condition (Upper Planes).</li>
				<li>Spectral wings appear on your back, giving you a flying speed of 40 feet.</li>
				<li>You have a +2 bonus to AC.</li>
				<li>All your weapon attacks are magical, and when you make a weapon attack, you can use your spellcasting ability modifier, instead of Strength or Dexterity, for the attack and damage rolls.</li>
				<li>You can attack twice, instead of once, when you take the Attack action on your turn. You ignore this benefit if you already have a feature, like Extra Attack, that lets you attack more than once when you take the Attack action on your turn.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">6</set>
			<set name="school">Transmutation</set>
			<set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">an object engraved with a symbol of the Outer Planes, worth at least 500 gp </set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
  <element name="Teleportation Circle" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_TELEPORTATION_CIRCLE">
    <supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>As you cast the spell, you draw a 10-foot-diameter circle on the ground inscribed with sigils that link your location to a permanent teleportation circle of your choice whose sigil sequence you know and that is on the same plane of existence as you. A shimmering portal opens within the circle you drew and remains open until the end of your next turn. Any creature that enters the portal instantly appears within 5 feet of the destination circle or in the nearest unoccupied space if that space is occupied. Many major temples, guilds, and other important places have permanent teleportation circles inscribed somewhere within their confines. Each such circle includes a unique sigil sequence - a string of magical runes arranged in a particular pattern. When you first gain the ability to cast this spell, you learn the sigil sequences for two destinations on the Material Plane, determined by the DM. You can learn additional sigil sequences during your adventures. You can commit a new sigil sequence to memory after studying it for 1 minute. You can create a permanent teleportation circle by casting this spell in the same location every day for one year. You need not use the circle to teleport when you cast the spell in this way.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">teleport</set>
      <set name="level">5</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 minute</set>
      <set name="duration">1 round</set>
      <set name="range">10 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">rare chalks and inks infused with precious gems with 50 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Vampiric Touch" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_VAMPIRIC_TOUCH">
    <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>The touch of your shadow-wreathed hand can siphon force from others to heal your wounds. Make a melee spell attack against a creature within your reach. On a hit, the target takes 3d6 necrotic damage, and you regain hit points equal to half the amount of necrotic damage dealt. Until the spell ends, you can make the attack again on each of your turns as an action.  </p>
      <p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the damage increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 3rd.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">necrotic</set>
      <set name="level">3</set>
      <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">Self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Warding Bond" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_WARDING_BOND">
    <supports>Cleric, Paladin</supports>
    <description>
      <p>This spell wards a willing creature you touch and creates a mystic connection between you and the target until the spell ends. While the target is within 60 feet of you, it gains a +1 bonus to AC and saving throws, and it has resistance to all damage. Also, each time it takes damage, you take the same amount of damage.</p>
      <p class="indent">The spell ends if you drop to 0 hit points or if you and the target become separated by more than 60 feet. It also ends if the spell is cast again on either of the connected creatures. You can also dismiss the spell as an action.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords"></set>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">1 hour</set>
      <set name="range">Touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
      <set name="materialComponent">a pair of platinum rings worth at least 50 gp each, which you and target must wear for the duration</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>  
  <element name="Weird" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_WEIRD">
    <supports>Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>Drawing on the deepest fears of a group of creatures, you create illusory creatures in their minds, visible only to them. Each creature in a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on a point of your choice within range must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, a creature becomes frightened for the duration. The illusion calls on the creature’s deepest fears, manifesting its worst nightmares as an implacable threat. At the end of each of the frightened creature’s turns, it must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or take 4d10 psychic damage. On a successful save, the spell ends for that creature.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="keywords">psychic</set>
      <set name="level">9</set>
      <set name="school">Illusion</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">120 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
      <set name="materialComponent" />
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>  
  
    <!-- Summons Statblocks -->
  <element name="Aberrant Spirit" type="Information" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_ABERRATION_STATBLOCK">
    <description>
      <p><em>Medium aberration</em></p>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 11 + the level of the spell (natural armor)</li>
        <li><strong>Hit Points</strong>40 + 10 for each spell level above 4th</li>
        <li><strong>Speed</strong> 30 ft., fly 30 ft. (hover) (Beholderkin only)</li>
      </ul>
      <table style="text-align:center">
        <thead>
          <tr><td>STR</td><td>DEX</td><td>CON</td><td>INT</td><td>WIS</td><td>CHA</td></tr>
        </thead>
        <tr><td>16 (+3)</td><td>10 (+0)</td><td>15 (+2)</td><td>16 (+3)</td><td>10 (+0)</td><td>6 (-2)</td></tr>
      </table>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Damage Immunities</strong> psychic</li>
        <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 60 ft., passive Perception 10</li>
        <li><strong>Languages</strong> Deep Speech, understands the languages you speak</li>
		<li><strong>Challenge</strong> — 	<strong>Proficiency Bonus</strong> equals your bonus.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><strong><em>Regeneration (Slaadi Only).</em></strong> The aberration regains 5 hit points at the start of its turn if it has at least 1 hit point.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Whispering Aura (Star Spawn Only).</em></strong> At the start of each of the aberration’s turns, each creature within 5 feet of the aberration must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or take 2d6 psychic damage, provided that the aberration isn’t incapacitated.</p>
      <h5 class="caption">ACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Multiattack.</em></strong> The aberration makes a number of attacks equal to half this spell’s level (rounded down).</p>
      <p><strong><em>Claws (Slaad Only).</em></strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 1d10 + 3 + the spell’s level slashing damage. If the target is a creature, it can’t regain hit points until the start of the aberration’s next turn.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Eye Ray (Beholderkin Only).</em></strong> <em>Ranged Spell Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, range 30 ft., one creature. <em>Hit:</em> 1d8 + 3 + the spell’s level psychic damage.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Psychic Slam (Star Spawn Only).</em></strong> <em>Melee Spell Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. Hit: 1d8 + 3 + the spell’s level psychic damage.</p>
    </description>
  </element>
  <element name="Bestial Spirit" type="Information" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_BEAST_STATBLOCK">
    <description>
      <p><em>Small beast</em></p>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 11 + the level of the spell (natural armor)</li>
        <li><strong>Hit Points</strong> 20 (Air only) or 30 (Land and Water only) + 5 for each spell level above 2nd</li>
        <li><strong>Speed</strong> 30 ft., climb 30 ft. (Land only), fly 60 ft. (Air only), swim 30 ft. (Water only)</li>
      </ul>
      <table style="text-align:center">
        <thead>
          <tr><td>STR</td><td>DEX</td><td>CON</td><td>INT</td><td>WIS</td><td>CHA</td></tr>
        </thead>
        <tr><td>18 (+4)</td><td>11 (+0)</td><td>16 (+3)</td><td>4 (-4)</td><td>14 (+2)</td><td>5 (-3)</td></tr>
      </table>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 60 ft., passive Perception 12</li>
        <li><strong>Languages</strong> understands the languages you speak</li>
		<li><strong>Challenge</strong> — 	<strong>Proficiency Bonus</strong> equals your bonus</li>
      </ul>
      <p><strong><em>Flyby (Air Only).</em></strong> The beast doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks when it flies out of an enemy’s reach.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Pack Tactics (Land and Water Only).</em></strong> The beast has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the beast’s allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn’t incapacitated.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Water Breathing (Water Only).</em></strong> The beast can breathe only underwater.</p>
      <h5 class="caption">ACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Multiattack.</em></strong> The beast makes a number of attacks equal to half this spell’s level (rounded down).</p>
      <p><strong><em>Maul.</em></strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 1d8 + 4 + the spell’s level piercing damage.</p>
    </description>
  </element>
  <element name="Celestial Spirit" type="Information" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_CELESTIAL_STATBLOCK">
    <description>
      <p><em>Large celestial</em></p>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 11 + the level of the spell (natural armor) + 2 (Defender only)</li>
        <li><strong>Hit Points</strong> 40 + 10 for each spell level above 5th</li>
        <li><strong>Speed</strong> 30 ft., fly 40 ft.</li>
      </ul>
      <table style="text-align:center">
        <thead>
          <tr><td>STR</td><td>DEX</td><td>CON</td><td>INT</td><td>WIS</td><td>CHA</td></tr>
        </thead>
        <tr><td>16 (+3)</td><td>14 (+2)</td><td>16 (+3)</td><td>10 (+0)</td><td>14 (+2)</td><td>16 (+3)</td></tr>
      </table>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Damage Resistances</strong> radiant</li>
        <li><strong>Condition Immunities</strong> charmed, frightened</li>
        <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 60 ft., passive Perception 12</li>
        <li><strong>Languages</strong> Celestial, understands the languages you speak</li>
		<li><strong>Challenge</strong> — 	<strong>Proficiency Bonus</strong> equals your bonus.</li>
      </ul>
      <h5 class="caption">ACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Multiattack.</em></strong> The celestial makes a number of attacks equal to half this spell’s level (rounded down).</p>
      <p><strong><em>Radiant Bow (Avenger Only).</em></strong> <em>Ranged Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, range 150/600 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 2d6 + 2 + the spell’s level radiant damage.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Radiant Mace (Defender Only).</em></strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 1d10 + 3 + the spell’s level radiant damage, and the celestial can choose itself or another creature it can see within 10 feet of the target. The chosen creature gains 1d10 temporary hit points.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Healing Touch (1/Day).</em></strong> The celestial touches another creature. The target magically regains hit points equal to 2d8 + the spell’s level.</p>
    </description>
  </element>
  <element name="Construct Spirit" type="Information" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_CONSTRUCT_STATBLOCK">
    <description>
      <p><em>Medium construct</em></p>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 13 + the level of the spell (natural armor)</li>
        <li><strong>Hit Points</strong>40 + 15 for each spell level above 4th.</li>
        <li><strong>Speed</strong> 30 ft</li>
      </ul>
      <table style="text-align:center">
        <thead>
          <tr><td>STR</td><td>DEX</td><td>CON</td><td>INT</td><td>WIS</td><td>CHA</td></tr>
        </thead>
        <tr><td>18 (+4)</td><td>10 (+0)</td><td>18 (+4)</td><td>14 (+2)</td><td>11 (+0)</td><td>5 (-3)</td></tr>
      </table>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Damage Resistances</strong> poison</li>
        <li><strong>Condition Immunities</strong> charmed, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</li>
        <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 60 ft, passive Perception 10</li>
        <li><strong>Languages</strong> understands the languages you speak</li>
		<li><strong>Challenge</strong> — 	<strong>Proficiency Bonus</strong> equals your bonus.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><strong><em>Heated Body (Metal Only).</em></strong> A creature that touches the construct or hits it with a melee attack while within 5 feet of it takes 1d10 fire damage.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Stone Lethargy (Stone Only).</em></strong> When a creature the construct can see starts its turn within 10 feet of the construct, the construct can force it to make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the target can't use reactions and its speed is halved until the start of its next turn.</p>
      <h5 class="caption">ACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Multiattack.</em></strong> The construct makes a number of attacks equal to half the spell's level (rounded down).</p>
      <p><strong><em>Slam.</em></strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft, one target. <em>Hit:</em> 1d8 + 4 + the spell's level bludgeoning damage.</p>
      <h5 class="caption">REACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Berserk Lashing (Clay Only).</em></strong> When the construct takes damage, it makes a slam attack against a random creature within 5 feet of it. If no creature is within reach, the construct moves up to half its speed towards an enemy it can see, without provoking opportunity attacks.</p>
    </description>
  </element>
  <element name="Elemental Spirit" type="Information" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_ELEMENTAL_STATBLOCK">
    <description>
      <p><em>Medium elemental</em></p>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 11 + the level of the spell (natural armor)</li>
        <li><strong>Hit Points</strong> 30 + 10 for each spell level above 4th</li>
        <li><strong>Speed</strong> 40 ft., burrow 40 ft. (Earth only), fly 40 ft. (hover) (Air only), swim 40 ft. (Water only)</li>
      </ul>
      <table style="text-align:center">
        <thead>
          <tr><td>STR</td><td>DEX</td><td>CON</td><td>INT</td><td>WIS</td><td>CHA</td></tr>
        </thead>
        <tr><td>18 (+4)</td><td>15 (+2)</td><td>17 (+3)</td><td>4 (-4)</td><td>10 (+0)</td><td>16 (+3)</td></tr>
      </table>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Damage Resistances</strong> acid (Water only), lightning and thunder (Air only); piercing and slashing (Earth only);</li>
        <li><strong>Damage Immunities</strong> poison; fire (Fire only)</li>
        <li><strong>Condition Immunities</strong> exhaustion, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, unconscious</li>
        <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 60 ft., passive Perception 10</li>
        <li><strong>Languages</strong> Primordial, understands the languages you speak</li>
		<li><strong>Challenge</strong> — 	<strong>Proficiency Bonus</strong> equals your bonus.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><strong><em>Amorphous Form (Air, Fire, and Water Only).</em></strong> The elemental can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch wide without squeezing.</p>
      <h5 class="caption">ACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Multiattack.</em></strong> The elemental makes a number of attacks equal to half this spell’s level (rounded down).</p>
      <p><strong><em>Slam.</em></strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 1d10 + 4 + the spell’s level bludgeoning damage (Air, Earth, and Water only) or fire damage (Fire only).</p>
    </description>
  </element>
  <element name="Fey Spirit" type="Information" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_FEY_STATBLOCK">
    <description>
      <p><em>Small fey</em></p>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 12 + the level of the spell (natural armor)</li>
        <li><strong>Hit Points</strong> 30 + 10 for each spell level above 3rd</li>
        <li><strong>Speed</strong> 40 ft.</li>
      </ul>
      <table style="text-align:center">
        <thead>
          <tr><td>STR</td><td>DEX</td><td>CON</td><td>INT</td><td>WIS</td><td>CHA</td></tr>
        </thead>
        <tr><td>13 (+1)</td><td>16 (+3)</td><td>14 (+2)</td><td>14 (+2)</td><td>11 (+0)</td><td>16 (+3)</td></tr>
      </table>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Condition Immunities</strong> charmed</li>
        <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 60 ft., passive Perception 10</li>
        <li><strong>Languages</strong> Sylvan, understands the languages you speak</li>
		<li><strong>Challenge</strong> — 	<strong>Proficiency Bonus</strong> equals your bonus</li>
      </ul>
      <h5 class="caption">ACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Multiattack.</em></strong> The fey makes a number of attacks equal to half this spell’s level (rounded down).</p>
      <p><strong><em>Shortsword.</em></strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 1d6 + 3 + the spell’s level piercing damage + 1d6 force damage.</p>
      <h5 class="caption">BONUS ACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Fey Step.</em></strong> The fey magically teleports up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space it can see. Then one of the following effects occurs, based on the fey's chosen mood:</p>
      <p><strong><em>Fuming.</em></strong> The fey has advantage on the next attack roll it makes before the end of its turn.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Mirthful.</em></strong> The fey can force a creature it can see within 10 feet of it to make on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. Unless the save succeeds, the target is charmed by you and the fey for 1 minute or until the target takes any damage.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Tricksy.</em></strong> The fey can fill a 5-foot cube within 5 feet of it with magical darkness, which lasts until the end of the its next turn.</p>
    </description>
  </element>
  <element name="Fiendish Spirit" type="Information" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_FIEND_STATBLOCK">
    <description>
      <p><em>Large fiend</em></p>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 12 + the level of the spell (natural armor)</li>
        <li><strong>Hit Points</strong> 50 (Demon only) or 40 (Devil only) or 60 (Yugoloth only) + 15 for each spell level above 6th</li>
        <li><strong>Speed</strong> 40 ft., climb 40 ft. (Demon only), fly 60 ft. (Devil only)</li>
      </ul>
      <table style="text-align:center">
        <thead>
          <tr><td>STR</td><td>DEX</td><td>CON</td><td>INT</td><td>WIS</td><td>CHA</td></tr>
        </thead>
        <tr><td>13 (+1)</td><td>16 (+3)</td><td>15 (+2)</td><td>10 (+0)</td><td>10 (+0)</td><td>16 (+3)</td></tr>
      </table>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Damage Resistances</strong> fire</li>
        <li><strong>Damage Immunities</strong> poison</li>
        <li><strong>Condition Immunities</strong> poisoned</li>
        <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 60 ft., passive Perception 10</li>
        <li><strong>Languages</strong> Abyssal, Infernal, telepathy 60 ft.</li>
        <li><strong>Challenge</strong> — 	<strong>Proficiency Bonus</strong> equals your bonus</li>
      </ul>
      <p><strong><em>Death Throes (Demon Only).</em></strong> When the fiend drops to 0 hit points or the spell ends, the fiend explodes, and each creature within 10 feet of it must make a Dexterity saving throw against your spell save DC. A creature takes 2d10 + this spell’s level fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Devil’s Sight (Devil Only).</em></strong> Magical darkness doesn’t impede the fiend’s darkvision.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Magic Resistance.</em></strong> The fiend has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</p>
      <h5 class="caption">ACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Multiattack.</em></strong> The fiend makes a number of attacks equal to half this spell’s level (rounded down).</p>
      <p><strong><em>Bite (Demon Only).</em></strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 1d12 + 3 + the spell’s level necrotic damage.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Claws (Yugoloth Only).</em></strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 1d8 + 3 + the spell’s level slashing damage. Immediately after the attack hits or misses, the fiend can magically teleport up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space it can see.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Hurl Flame (Devil Only).</em></strong> <em>Ranged Spell Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, range 150 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 2d6 + 3 + the spell’s level fire damage. If the target is a flammable object that isn’t being worn or carried, it also catches fire.</p>
    </description>
  </element>
  <element name="Shadow Spirit" type="Information" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_SHADOWSPAWN_STATBLOCK">
    <description>
      <p><em>Medium monstrosity</em></p>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 11 + the level of the spell (natural armor)</li>
        <li><strong>Hit Points</strong> 35 + 15 for each spell level above 3rd</li>
        <li><strong>Speed</strong> 40 ft.</li>
      </ul>
      <table style="text-align:center">
        <thead>
          <tr><td>STR</td><td>DEX</td><td>CON</td><td>INT</td><td>WIS</td><td>CHA</td></tr>
        </thead>
        <tr><td>13 (+1)</td><td>16 (+3)</td><td>15 (+2)</td><td>4 (-4)</td><td>10 (+0)</td><td>16 (+3)</td></tr>
      </table>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Damage Resistances</strong> necrotic</li>
        <li><strong>Condition Immunities</strong> frightened</li>
        <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 120 ft., passive Perception 10</li>
        <li><strong>Languages</strong> understands the languages you speak</li>
        <li><strong>Challenge</strong> — 	<strong>Proficiency Bonus</strong> equals your bonus</li>
      </ul>
      <p><strong><em>Terror Frenzy (Fury Only).</em></strong> The spirit has advantage on attack rolls against frightened creatures.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Weight of Sorrow (Despair Only).</em></strong> Any creature, other than you, that starts its turn within 5 feet of the spirit has its speed reduced by 20 feet until the start of that creature's next turn.</p>
      <h5 class="caption">ACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Multiattack.</em></strong> The spirit makes a number of attacks equal to half this spell’s level (rounded down).</p>
      <p><strong><em>Chilling Rend.</em></strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 1d12 + 3 + the spell’s level cold damage.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Dreadful Scream (1/Day).</em></strong> The spirit screams. Each creature within 30 feet of it must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or be frightened of the spirit for 1 minute. The frightened creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</p>
      <h5 class="caption">BONUS ACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Shadow Stealth (Fear Only).</em></strong> While in dim light or darkness, the spirit takes the Hide action.</p>
    </description>
  </element>
  <element name="Undead Spirit" type="Information" source="Tasha's Cauldron of Everything" id="ID_TCOE_INFORMATION_SUMMON_UNDEAD_STATBLOCK">
    <description>
      <p><em>Medium undead</em></p>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 11 + the level of the spell (natural armor)</li>
        <li><strong>Hit Points</strong> 30 (Ghostly and Putrid only) or 20 (Skeletal only) + 10 for each spell level above 3rd</li>
        <li><strong>Speed</strong> 30 ft., fly 40 ft. (hover) (Ghostly only)</li>
      </ul>
      <table style="text-align:center">
        <thead>
          <tr><td>STR</td><td>DEX</td><td>CON</td><td>INT</td><td>WIS</td><td>CHA</td></tr>
        </thead>
        <tr><td>12 (+1)</td><td>16 (+3)</td><td>15 (+2)</td><td>4 (-4)</td><td>10 (+0)</td><td>9 (-1)</td></tr>
      </table>
      <ul class="unstyled mb">
        <li><strong>Damage Immunities</strong> necrotic, poison</li>
        <li><strong>Condition Immunities</strong> exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned</li>
        <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 60 ft., passive Perception 10</li>
        <li><strong>Languages</strong> understands the languages you speak</li>
        <li><strong>Challenge</strong> — 	<strong>Proficiency Bonus</strong> equals your bonus</li>
      </ul>
      <p><strong><em>Festering Aura (Putrid Only).</em></strong> Any creature, other than you, that starts its turn within 5 feet of the spirit must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC or be poisoned until the start of its next turn.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Incorporeal Passage (Ghostly Only).</em></strong> The spirit can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. If it ends its turn inside an object, it is shunted to the nearest unoccupied space and takes 1d10 force damage for every 5 feet traveled.</p>
      <h5 class="caption">ACTIONS</h5>
      <p><strong><em>Multiattack.</em></strong> The spirit makes a number of attacks equal to half this spell’s level (rounded down).</p>
      <p><strong><em>Deathly Touch (Ghostly Only).</em></strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. <em>Hit:</em> 1d8 + 3 + the spell’s level necrotic damage, and the creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or be frightened of the undead until the end of the target’s next turn.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Grave Bolt (Skeletal Only).</em></strong> <em>Ranged Spell Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, range 150 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 2d4 + 3 + the spell’s level necrotic damage.</p>
      <p><strong><em>Rotting Claw (Putrid Only).</em></strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> your spell attack modifier to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 1d6 + 3 + the spell’s level slashing damage. If the target is poisoned, it must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC or be paralyzed until the end of its next turn.</p>
    </description>
  </element>
</elements>
